There are so many gurus online,
especially on YouTube,
telling personal trainers,
"If you want to go online,
work from Bali remote, make
$15,000 a month,
then just follow these steps."
But there's a big
issue that no one's really talking about.
All of these gurus have made all of their
money not from fitness businesses.
They made their money from selling coaches
the dream.
No sales calls, sell in DMs.
You don't even need a sales funnel.
And let's be honest,
you get a desperate personal trainer,
put them on a sales
call, say, "Hey, pay me $10,000
and I'll make your dreams come true."
You're going
to have a pretty nice house
and a pretty nice car because there's a
lot of
desperate personal trainers. The market
is more saturated than ever.
There's more competition than ever.
People spending is lower than ever.
So why should you listen to me? Well,
my name is James Smith,
and I actually have
an eight-figure fitness business that's
had over 117,000 clients.
I've actually run
and operated a fitness business,
not made a fortune from selling
people the dream about running a business.
Now,
just before we get into all of the stages
that are necessary, let me be honest
with you, like most gurus aren't.
Out of that eight figures
that the business has
made, it's not made me ultra wealthy,
because all of that money I've earned
isn't
just mine. I have a business partner.
He gets half. I have my amazing coaches.
They get a huge amount of it.
But what my business has done over the
last seven
years is given me a life of freedom.
I haven't had to go to work for seven
years.
I work remote.
I can live in any country I want.
I've accrued the level of wealth where I
fly business class minimum wherever I go.
But I'll still happily buy a car that's a
year and a half old.
I've accrued the level of wealth where I
can buy all my friends dinner whenever we
go,
but my house only has one spare bedroom.
I'm not even here today promising you
that you can make millions.
Instead,
I'm going to teach you how to operate
and run a business where you can
have more free time,
you can earn enough to hopefully lay down
on a plane, and
better yet, use your time more wisely.
Because when I created this system,
I had more hours spare,
which meant I could
write a book, then two books,
then three books, then do the events
and tours that
come with them,
and then eventually build a personal brand
big enough to start
other projects.
My online coaching business gave me the
life of freedom.
My life of freedom
is actually what made me a little bit
rich. Let's get into it.
If you want to have an online business,
first of all, you need to have a business.
Now,
just before we get into the first step,
and probably the most important step,
let's take a quick tangent.
What we really need is a brand.
And a brand, in my belief,
is where your personality meets your
business. If you go too heavy with,
let's say, the information
that you're giving
across and just information,
you become ChatGPT.
If you care too much about your
personality and think you're bigger
and more
important than you are,
you end up making vlogs.
However,
if you can take a good fingering joke
and intertwine it with the
information that your audience needs,
you're going to discover a brand.
So it's really important
that you get your personality across in
your content, in
everything. The biggest mistake
that people are making
when it comes to brand is
they think they need to be a business.
@BetterYouPT, @ActiveHealth,
@FitForever. No, you are the brand.
I'm James Smith.
He's Declan Jenkinson. Alex Warme
is Alex Warme.
Chris Williamson is Chris Williamson.
Chris Williamson isn't Modern Wisdom.
Modern Wisdom is Chris's podcast.
Now, sure, when the studio bills get paid,
probably Modern Wisdom pay that, not
Chris himself. But he doesn't walk around,
"Hi, I'm Modern Wisdom.
You can call me Chris." All of your
clients pay you, not your business.
They're not paying Better You PT.
They're paying Dave. They're paying Sarah.
The quicker that you can represent your
brand as yourself, the better.
Unless you're a team of five people all
building the same brand, you are your
brand. Get your name handle.
The only reason I have PT in my name
is because I'm
called James Smith.
I've got the most common,
boring white name in the world.
And the only way
that I got the James Smith handle,
I had to have a fight with
another guy called James Smith, and I won.
The next component is
when I say you need to have a business,
you need to have a
business. There are people
that want to get into online coaching
that have never
done any coaching. They're like, "Oh,
I've trained my friends." Okay,
so you have
zero experience. Trust me when I say this,
behind all great online
coaches is a coach that
was great in person. Yep. Okay.
And what we're going to do now
is we know your lower back's a little bit
sore with
the bent over row,
so we're going to do some TRX rows.
As far as the rep range,
we're going to do between 8 to 12.
Reason being is we've done the reps.
I've done 5,000 hours of coaching in
person.
You may think that it would be amazing for
you to go work online with a laptop.
And although these sessions in the gym may
be on paper some of your least paid
hours,
these will pay you dividends way into the
future.
Because all of those sessions
that I sat talking to my clients,
chatting to my
clients,
putting the weights away from my clients,
I became an expert in my
clients. In the advertising space online,
we have something called a lookalike
audience.
Let's say we're selling the course that's
in the link to this
description, the PT Start Kit,
where you get a short-form content
creation course
and everything you need to know about
launching a PT business.
And let's say it's $99.
Link in description. We've sold 4,000
or 5,000 of those.
I can say to Meta,
"Find me a lookalike audience."
And what it will do is it will
find all of the things
that those people have in common
and create me a brand-new
audience to advertise to
that have all the same traits.
And lookalike audience ads absolutely
bang. Why?
Because they're just like the people
that bought the course.
Why am I telling you this? The people
that pay you for in-person coaching
are the
exact same people that
are going to pay you for online coaching.
They have the same problems.
They have the same demographics.
They probably just live a bit further
away.
So no matter where you are, trust me
when I say this. Find a facility.
Do some in-person sessions.
Those conversations
that you have with your clients
allow you to understand them.
The same way the reason I got you to click
this video
is I know you.
I've actually been you before,
and now I work with thousands of you.
I know what you think about
when you wake up.
I probably even know what type of genre of
porn you watch. Dirty bugger.
If you want to take your business online,
you have to have a bricks-and-mortar
business in the onset. Now,
if you have a gym, if you have a facility,
but you
haven't got any clients,
going online could take you weeks
and months to get your
first client.
So you probably will need to do some kind
of face-to-face marketing.
Walking the floor. Underrated.
Truth be told, rewind about 10 years,
I used to do
this thing where I'd PT.
I'd do like eight or nine sessions in a
day.
And just as I went to get my car keys
and put them in my pocket, I'd go, "James,
go
talk to 10 people." It'd be 8:00 PM at
night, and I'd go around the gym, and I
would pray that no one wanted to talk.
Because I didn't set the success as being
I need to get a consult or book people
in.
My success was they've just got to book a
session.
So I grab my keys, go around. "Hey, mate.
You guys all right? Good.
We got some heavyweights over there
if you want them. You need anything? Cool.
You have a good night." "Hey,
just to let you know, these pins
are a little bit out
of whack.
Just going to move this down for you.
I'm James, by the way.
I'm just on my way out of here, but
if you ever need anything, I'm in the gym.
You have a good night." Go to the next
one. "Oh, sorry to interrupt.
The other PTs,
they always put these TRXs in wrong,
and the last thing I'd want
is for you to slip over and hurt yourself.
My name's James.
I'm one of the PTs here.
I'm one of the only ones
that actually knows what they're
doing. I'm not here to sell you anything,
but if you ever need anything, just come
find me. My details are on the PT board.
There you go.
You have a good night." Then I'd just get
to the last one.
I'd be like, "Oh,
you guys all right there?" "Excuse me.
How much is personal training?" Fuck.
I'd actually be annoyed
that I've now got to go talk to this,
but I just wanted to
talk to 10 people and go home. "Hey, mate.
So I don't discuss pricing on the floor.
But what we can do
is why don't we book in a consult?
I'll take you through a little
conversation, we'll talk about your goals.
We'll do a little half-hour session.
You can decide whether
or not you like me or not. No obligation.
Look,
even if you think you're wasting my time,
you're not.
It's good for me to be seen on the gym
floor with people. When are you next free?
Book someone in for Tuesday." Boom.
Some people out there think they can just
talk to five people.
No, dozens of people.
When I worked in door-to-door sales,
I had to knock on 100
doors to make one sale. Trust me.
In the world of personal training,
you have 100
conversations,
you've got at least five consults,
of which four show up, of which
three become clients.
Even the shortest of short-term clients
buy a bundle of at
least 10.
So even in the poorest parts of England,
that's
£300 for a conversation.
Without understanding your demographic
and their
problems,
we can't even get into stage one.
Content is a bit like martial arts.
When you begin, you're useless.
And every time,
it's not about becoming a black
belt, it's about becoming
that little bit less useless.
You can't lean on content to bring you
clients, because for some people, it will
take six months, for some,
it will take 12 months, for others,
it will take three
weeks. Your business
is your backbone to begin with,
and then eventually,
content is your way out of here.
It's your way off the floor.
But you must do it right.
First thing we're going to talk about
is problems.
People don't want to see your workout.
They don't give a fuck what your workout
of the day was. Get ready with me.
They don't give a fuck. Here's my lunch.
No one gives a shit.
When I'm walking the floor
and I'm trying to get new clients,
I'm solving problems.
"Hey, do you need me help with something?
How does this strap work?
Let me teach you." Get my phone out. TRX.
Cool.
Another client says to me, "James,
what are macros?" Suddenly,
when I go home from
that day at work,
I know I'm making two videos.
Yeah, I've just finished with my clients.
Say to someone, "Hey,
can you just hold a camera for a second?
If you're someone
that uses one of these in the gym
and you're not sure how it
works,
I'm going to give you three ways you can
use this, and it's going to beat
using a barbell." Maybe another one.
"If you're someone that's intimidated by
heavy weights or you actually don't want
to step foot in a squat rack,
this TRX means that you can get all of the
workouts
that you need,
and you can do it from the functional
training room of your gym."
Cool. The next problem might be macros.
"If you're someone in fitness that's heard
the term macros, you don't understand
it,
I'm going to use these three bowls of
Skittles to help you understand." If you
solve people's problems in your content,
think about what a personal trainer
is.
We are hiring someone because you have a
problem.
Declan here solves a problem for me.
My arms aren't long enough to hold the
camera that far away.
I don't want to be moving a tripod around
all the time.
I pay Declan to make my problems go away.
My next problem is I need to go back
and feed my son shortly.
Declan's going to edit.
Take away a problem.
When people hire a personal trainer,
they don't go to the gym.
They solve the problem of keeping them
accountable. They don't follow a program.
The personal trainer solves the problem of
giving them a program.
They don't do a diet unless they're told
what to do.
Personal trainer solves a problem. We
are in the business of problem-solving.
React content,
you can react to things you agree with,
disagree with.
What are you doing? You
are problem-solving because people see
stuff online,
they're not sure if it's true.
You can be the voice of reason.
This is what really happens
when you take creatine.
This is why you shouldn't consider the
carnivore diet.
This is what it could be like if you
were to take a GLP-1 agonist.
I've worked with over 1,300 fitness
coaches in the last year.
Every time someone complains to me about
not having enough clients or not enough
people joining their 12-week challenge
or not enough people inquire for business
or
that no one bought
when they put an email out about whatever
offer it was, there
are two things I need to know. What
is the size of your socials?
How many people are on your email list?
20% of your total amount of followers
should be on your email list.
So if you've got 2,000 followers
and you don't have 400 people on your
email list,
there is a problem. You need to go out
and make sure that your content at the end
of it has a call to action where you can
get their email address.
Maybe you put a chatbot. Maybe you put,
"If you want to work out your macros,
comment the word carbs." Then
when you work out their calories for them,
you also
give them a link to join your email list
so they can stay in the loop and find out
more.
If you do have 20% of your total following
on an email list, you should
probably focus on growing your audience.
Wherever I see people struggling to sell
stuff online, there is a bottleneck.
Their following is either nonexistent,
they need to put out more content,
or their
following is okay, but their email list
is terribly small, which means they've not
spent enough time converting.
They've been putting all of their content
creation
energy into getting engagement, views,
and vanity metrics, and they've not
converted any of that into data.
I could go out on a night out, not now,
10 years
ago, and chat up loads of women,
and people go, "James, you stud.
I saw you talking to at least 15 girls
last night." But if I got no numbers, what
was the point?
To look good in front of my friends?
Whereas if I'd only spoken to five girls
and got five numbers, you'd be doing a lot
more damage, allegedly.
So much of people's problems
when it comes to going
online sit here. We have the preface
that some people want to be an online
coach
and never done a coaching session before,
but let's park that to the side.
People do not have enough data from their
existing following, which can lead people
onto how. How do you get people's emails?
Before 2025,
you could have probably offered someone an
e-book that they don't read
or put in a calorie calculator.
But it's 2025.
These methods have been rinsed.
One trend that I see dominating at the
moment is
creating some kind of value autoresponder.
You could automate 20, 30, 50 emails.
You pre-write them,
and they go out in a sequence of one, two,
three, four, five,
six, all the way to 50.
Each one of those emails could address a
certain point and
problem that someone's facing,
and over time,
that automation will wear them down
to the point they will start
or consider using you in your business.
Then you only have to write it once.
A really good automation regarding your
specialty, whether it's developing the
gluteals, whether it's losing fat,
whether it's becoming proficient at boxing
on a
bag, whatever it is.
If you can't put together 30, 40,
or 50 emails
that go out once a day
that make someone really confident
that you're the person to
solve their problems,
then maybe you shouldn't be doing this as
a job.
If you can't put out one piece of content
a day, maybe you shouldn't be doing this
as a job.
And I didn't say it had to be a perfect
production.
You're not Oppenheimer.
You're not producing an Oppenheimer.
Then from that data, from those people,
whether an automation or whether you want
to send broadcasts,
you send them to a landing page.
Now again,
one of the biggest mistakes people
are making, they're hosting this on
AWeber, Mailchimp, Squarespace.
It looks shit.
It doesn't look nice. You're like, "Oh,
but my coaching is really good." If you
turn up to a first date with smelly breath
and dirty trainers, trust me, bro, she
ain't going down there.
So many people will do the in-hour
sessions.
They will put out content every day.
They'll run an email marketing list.
They'll create a bottleneck by having a
shitty-looking landing page.
ClickFunnels or Leadpages,
both of them So good.
Oh, it's $40 a month. Listen, mate,
it's cheaper than a member of staff, I can
assure you.
This is where a lot of other gurus will
say, "Get them on a call, get
them on a phone, pressure them into sales,
get them onto the sales team,
get them on the phone." Listen,
you've already got people
that you're giving hours
of your time to in person.
When you're not doing that,
you're creating good
content.
When you're not creating good content,
you're nurturing an email list.
When you're not doing that,
you're creating variations of your landing
page, which
we'll get onto in a second.
Where the fuck are you supposed to find
two hours a day
to sit on calls with people where 45
minutes in they go, "I need to talk to my
husband."?
That will work for the short term.
Let me get this right.
Sales calls work, but as this grows,
this gets bigger, and this grows,
those amounts of calls
are only ever going up.
So if your business thrives,
if your business does well,
if your business is going
in the direction we want it to go,
whatever amount of sales calls you've got
now,
to double your business,
you need double the amount of sales calls.
What are you going to do?
Pay someone else to go on it? Maybe.
Or instead,
you make your landing page better.
The way you do that
is by creating A/B splits.
You create what you think
is a good landing page,
or you join my program and I'll
teach you how to do it.
Link in the description.
You create a brief version,
a long version. One with a video,
one without a video.
Lead pages will then split the traffic
between your landing pages and
you get to see in real time
which one yields the best result.
And you can then go, wow, okay.
Landing page B that didn't have much text
but had a
really good VSL video that
was only one and a half minutes long got
twice the
conversions of the longer page.
I thought people wanted loads of
information about
my program,
but the statistics show me
that the briefer version actually does
more. So what could you do then?
You create three versions of
that landing page.
Now, a lot of other gurus are going to go,
"Why are you getting so complex, man?
Why are you trying to make this so
complex?
Just get them on the phone." This does
take time, but every time you do this and
spend a few hours doing it,
your sales process gets better.
It's only going to go up from 4%,
and then before you know it, 6%, 7%,
8%. Now, that can seem trivial,
but imagine this.
Same business, same in-person coach.
Content starts performing better,
but even if it doesn't,
emails start performing
better, but even if they don't.
If your landing page can double its
conversion,
that's twice the amount of business from
the same process.
Same content, same gym, same hours,
same wake-up time, same go-to-sleep time,
double the business. This, I believe,
should be done without ever going near a
sales call. Because although they work,
you need to preserve every single bit of
energy that you have being a good coach,
putting out good content, writing good
emails, nurturing your landing page,
and making it better.
Now,
I wish I could make this video longer,
but it wouldn't be fair on the
thousands of coaches that pay me.
But here's a bonus that you can take away.
Give them the MBG,
the money-back guarantee.
Now, this can be in person
and it can also be online.
In your landing page,
or maybe even in your emails,
just say to them, "If you don't
love the coaching,
let me know within the first month,
I'll refund you in full."
That will triple your sales.
And maybe 5% of people will ask for a
refund, but
that's okay. For five times more sales,
that's a good deal.
Not to mention,
if they hate your product for whatever
reason, even if they're
mental, just give them their money back.
You don't want a bitter,
unsavory customer.
Look at these other mentorships online.
The other business mentorships who rip off
the coaches in their course.
They go onto threads online.
They're all over Reddit saying,
"This person ripped me
off.
This person sent me legal letters." You
don't want that.
Give them the money-back guarantee.
It will also help you with the way
that you communicate your sale.
And that's Online Coaching with James
Smith. Affordable online coaching my app.
In the first two weeks,
if you don't love it for whatever reason,
even after we've
sent you the program, you let us know,
we'll refund you in full. That's legit.
I will give you one more bonus thing just
to piss off the other coaches.
This is the bit where the other business
gurus are going to get really, really
annoyed. Some of you
are trying to charge high ticket prices
because it's a premium
product. What you have is amazing.
Sorry, it's a workout, it's some macros,
and it's someone to chat to.
It's great, but it's not amazing.
So what they'll say to you, you have your
one-month price of weeks, but they'll go,
"Nah, let's times that by three.
Let's sell them 12 weeks premium."
But then what they'll also say to you
is, "Six-month upfront." This
is the word they love. Commitment.
Commitment.
I need a six-month upfront commitment.
Do you know why they're telling you to do
this?
Because you will get six months of cash
flow up front.
So let's say you're a PT, you charge,
I don't know,
200 pounds a month for online
coaching. Cool. Times that by six.
That's 1,200 pounds.
So you're getting 1,200 from a customer,
let's say in January.
Now you're going to get on sales calls
with, I don't know, what? 10 people?
15 people? That's easy to do.
You could do that in a week.
Suddenly, what's that, 16K?
That mentor then goes, "Well done, Declan.
You just hit 16K a month. What
were you making before,
Declan?" I don't know.
1,000 pounds, 1,500.
1,000 pounds sounds better.
"Declan, can you come to my house?
We're going to film some content.
Why don't you come around?" You come
around my house and I go, "Declan here was
only making 1,000 pounds a month before my
mentorship.
Now he's doing 16K a month."
But he's not doing 16K a month.
He did 16K in one month because he decided
to take
six months' worth of revenue from his
client and backhandle it all into one
month right now. This
is a vanity metric for the guru
that you've hired.
Not to make you look good,
not to help you,
but to make them look good.
To make it seem that the results
that you've got happened right now.
It's a farce.
And do you know what happens
when you make 16K in a month?
You take your foot off the gas.
You stop producing so much content.
You stop caring about your emails.
You're like, "I made 16 grand a month.
Everything's going up." Three,
four months' time,
you look at your cash flow and
you realize, whoa, I'm stuck.
I'm in a shitty position. Why?
Because you pressed
and squeezed people for six months' worth
of revenue.
Let me tell you this.
I work with you coaches.
The majority of you jump on a fucking
split pay. Why?
Because you don't want to give over the
cash all in one go.
If I reduce that down to a lower split
pay, you would take it. Do you know why?
For security.
You don't want to hand over all your cash
at once in case you need it
for something.
You will take the minimum payment
necessary to join my course.
And I'm in a position to help you make way
more money than what you pay for the
course. Your customers are the exact same.
You should be offering a monthly price
and a weekly price.
And it shouldn't be more expensive to be
weekly.
It can be a little bit,
economies of scale, commitment.
But wouldn't it be better for you to
reduce the barrier to entry for your
clients?
Rather than them needing 1,200 pounds to
use the services, why not just say it's 50
pounds a week? Because
if you're not shit at what you do,
they will stay.
And even if they leave, let them. "Oh,
but they've only paid me 50 pounds.
I wrote them a workout."
That did not take you an hour.
Because let's be honest,
you just signed up Steve,
and he reminded you a lot like
Pete that you onboarded three months ago.
And you just got Pete's workout,
phase one, and you put Steve on it.
So don't fucking cry
that someone left after one week because
all you did was
assign them someone else's program.
That's how online coaching works.
You'll end up with 1,000 different
templates,
but you just assign the best one to
them. They don't pay for novelty,
they pay for results.
They pay for accountability.
Charging people weekly
or monthly revenue won't give
me amazing screenshots
that I can use to bolster my own sales.
But it'll help you with your cash flow
and it will help you with the finger on
the
pulse of how well your business
is actually doing.
Then on a week-by-week basis,
you can see how your revenue looks to see
how much
attention you need to put into marketing
or nurturing.
Now, you will appreciate
that sounds very different to what
everyone else in the
industry says. Do you know why?
Because they're more optimized on running
their
business than your fitness business.
Hopefully that would've made a few light
bulbs go off.
If you want to work with me,
the link's in the descriptions.
And if you don't, well,
I'll see you in three months
when you've been ripped off by
the other guys.